Guide to the Metaphysical Society of America Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Metaphysical Society of America records
1951-1981
MS 1364
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(4 boxes)
The records consist of three parts: administrative records of the Metaphysical Society; communications from other philosophical societies made up of correspondence, announcements and publications; and selected offprints from The Review of Metaphysics (1963-1981).
Metaphysical Society of America
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard T. DeGeorge in 1983.
Arrangement
Arranged in seven series: I. Correspondence. II. Annual Meetings. III. Non-Financial Material. IV. Financial Records. V. Membership Lists. VI. Other Societies. VII. Reprints.
Scope and Contents
The Metaphysical Society of America was founded by Paul Weiss, Professor of Philosophy, in 1950 at New Haven. Professor Weiss' purpose was "to turn the attention of the philosophical community from more limited objectives to concern with questions about the nature of reality." With a nationwide membership of 112 in 1951, the Society has grown to over 600 members today with an international scope. Its members, which include professors, scholars, and laymen interested in questions of metaphyiscs, meet annually at various universities throughout the United States and Canada. The Society publishes annual announcements and membership lists and has a long-standing relationship with the Review of Metaphysics.
The material in this collection, donated March 29, 1983 by Richard T. DeGeorge, President of the Metaphysical Society, is divided into three series: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, OTHER SOCIETIES, REPRINTS FROM THE REVIEW OF METAPHYSICS. Series I, ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, consists of correspondence, information about the Society's annual meetings, financial records, membership specifics, and miscellaneous items. It is arranged chronologically according to subject matter. Series II, OTHER SOCIETIES, contains announcements, memoranda, reports, program information and some correspondence related to various philosophical organizations. Much of this material is from the American Council of Learned Societies of which MSA is an affiliate member. Series III comprises articles, arranged alphabetically by author, reprinted from the Review of Metaphysics.
Biographical / Historical
The Metaphysical Society of America was founded by Paul Weiss, Professor of Philosophy, Yale University, in 1950 at New Haven. Professor Weiss' purpose was "to turn the attention of the philosophical community from more limited objectives to concern with questions about the nature of reality."
Metaphysics; Philosophy; Weiss, Paul, 1901-2002; Metaphysical Society of America; Yale University. Philosophy Department
- Administrative Records, 1951-1980; Series I; 2' (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - General correspondence, 1951-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1-25)
    - Inquiries about dues, 1965-1967, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Klubertanz, George, 1950-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Prospective members, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Annual Meetings
    - Announcements, correspondence, programs, 1951-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29-48)
    - Announcements, correspondence, programs, 1973-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 49-57)
    - Minutes, 1956-1979 (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
  - Financial Records
    - Audits, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 60-68)
    - Bills (w/correspondence), 1959-1980 (Box 2, Folder 69-70)
    - Cancelled checks (w/correspondence), 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Dues, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Financial records, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Internal Revenue Service, 1971, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1957-1980 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Membership
    - Applications, 1957-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 76-85)
    - Invitations, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Lists, 1952-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 87-92)
    - Nomination forms, undated (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - State distribution, undated (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Announcements, 1959-1980 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Ballot forms, 1959-1977 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - "A Brief Account of the Metaphysical Society of America", undated (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Reports to MSA by Paul Kuntz, 1966, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Committees, 1958-1973 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Constitution, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Newsletter, 1971-1982 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Officers, undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Philosophy programs at U. S. universities, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Re: Paul Weiss, 1974, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
- Other Societies, 1959-1981; Series II; 1' (1 box)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1959-1976 (Box 3, Folder 105-110)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 111-117)
  - Canadian Philosophical Societies, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Conference of Philosophical Societies, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - International Federation of Philosophical Societies, 1972-1983 (Box 3, Folder 120-121)
  - International Society of Metaphysics, 1963-1980 (Box 3, Folder 122-123)
  - UNESCO, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - World Union of Catholic Philosophical Societies, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 125)
- Reprints from the Review of Metaphysics, 1963-1981; Series III; 1' (1 box)
  - Bertocci, Peter A. "Toward a Metaphysics of Creation", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Chisholm, Roderick M. "Parts as Essential to their Wholes", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Clarke, W. Norris "The Self as a Source of Meaning in Metaphysics", 1968 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Compton, John J. "Reinvesting the Philosophy of Nature", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Findlay, J. N. "The Three Hypostases of Platonism", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Harris, Errol E. "The Power of Reason", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Hocking, Richard "Event, Act, and Presence", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Leclerc, Ivor "The Metaphysics of the Good", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - McMullin, Ernan "Two Faces of Science", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - McMullin, Ernan "Compton on Philosophy of Nature", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Owens, Joseph "Reality and Metaphysics", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Randall, John Herman "Metaphysics and Language", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Reck, Andrew J. "Being and Substance", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Schmitz, Kenneth "A Gloss on Being, Immediacy, and Articulation", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Schmitz, Kenneth "A Memorial of Truth", 1980 (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - Smith, John E. "Being, Immediacy and Articulation", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Williams, Donald C. "Necessary Facts", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 142)